<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Politicall observations upon the fall of Seianus. Written in Italian by Gio. Baptista Manzini. And translated into English by Sr. T.H.</title>
            <title>Della peripetia di fortuna. English</title>
            <author>Manzini, Giovanni Battista, 1599-1664.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1634</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 60 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 27 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2012-10">2012-10 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A06858</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 17293</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S120752</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99855946</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99855946</idno>
            <idno type="VID">21457</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A06858)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 21457)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 559:05)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Politicall observations upon the fall of Seianus. Written in Italian by Gio. Baptista Manzini. And translated into English by Sr. T.H.</title>
                  <title>Della peripetia di fortuna. English</title>
                  <author>Manzini, Giovanni Battista, 1599-1664.</author>
                  <author>T. H., Sir (Thomas Hawkins), d. 1640.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[4], 48 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by Anne Griffin, for Godfrey Emondson [i.e. Emerson],</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1634.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>A translation of: Manzini, Giovanni Battista.  Della peripetia de fortuna.</note>
                  <note>Sir T.H. = Sir Thomas Hawkins.</note>
                  <note>Actual publisher's name from STC.</note>
                  <note>Identified as STC 17293b on UMI microfilm reel 812.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the Folger Shakespeare Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Sejanus, Lucius Aelius, d. 31.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2011-09</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-09</date>
            <label>Apex CoVantage</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-11</date>
            <label>Holly Beeman</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-11</date>
            <label>Holly Beeman</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:21457:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:21457:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>POLITICALL OBSERVATIONS Upon the fall of SEIANVS.</p>
            <p>Written in Italian by GIO. BAPTISTA MANZINI. And tranſlated into Engliſh by S<hi rend="sup">r</hi>. <hi>T. H.</hi>
            </p>
            <q>
               <bibl>JUVENAL.</bibl>
               <l>—<hi>Deſcendunt ſtatuae, reſtem<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan> ſequuntur.</hi>
               </l>
            </q>
            <figure>
               <figDesc>printer's device?</figDesc>
            </figure>
            <p>LONDON, Printed by <hi>Anne Griffin,</hi> for <hi>Godfrey Emondſon.</hi> 1634.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:21457:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:21457:2"/>
            <head>
               <hi>THE AVTHOVR</hi> to the Reader.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>He two firſt Bookes of the Life of <hi>Sejanus,</hi> diſtingui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhed into three, were caſually taken from me; as if For<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tune likewiſe perſecuting him on paper, would not ſuffer any memory of him to ſurvive, but ruine. I could have gathered them together againe, had I not feared ſome might have imagined me ambitious to ſtand in competition with him, who al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ready hath laboured on the ſame life. There live many Gentlemen in <hi>Flo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence,</hi> who ſaw mine, before that other
<pb facs="tcp:21457:3"/> paſſed the Mountaines. Notwithſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding I have not proceeded in this under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taking, as well becauſe the worke was then the birth of too greene an age in me, as for that I ſuppoſed this ſole remainder (the picture of a perfect Courtier) figured in the fall of this Vnhappy Man, might ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice to entertaine thee with contentment. Live free, and prejudicate not what my heart conceives of Fortune, for no ſooner ſhall you have led your eyes along to the end of this Booke, but will confeſſe, that of this diſeaſe of the world, my opinion hath bene very ſound.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:21457:3"/>
            <head>POLITICALL OBSERVATIONS Upon the fall of <hi>SEJANVS.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">M</seg>Ore cannot a man receive, nor more Fortune give. If ſhee raiſed not <hi>Sejanus</hi> to Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>galitie, it was becauſe ſhee thought it a leſſe matter to af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ford a head for Empire, than to reſigne the head of Empire over as a prey to one who ſhould tyrannize it. Here either wea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry, or repentant, ſhe began to forſake <hi>Sejanus.</hi> Health, Wit, Riches, Incenſe, and Scepters, were gifts to have impoveriſhed the giver her ſelfe, had ſhee not even whilſt ſhe gave them, with a covetous hand, ſnatched them backe againe.</p>
            <pb n="2" facs="tcp:21457:4"/>
            <p>He borne at <hi>Vulſinium,</hi> (at that time a rich Towne of <hi>Tuſcanie,</hi> which was afterward con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſumed by lightning, heaven alwayes aiming to thunder-ſtrike, where any pretend above hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mane condition) was advanced by Fortune to Courts, offices, dignities, truſt of a Prince, ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pereminencie over all, and laſtly to Altars and Incenſe. He had derogated from the condition of man, and not beene tyrannized, but the ty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rant of Fate, if he had with equalitie of fortune concluded the beginning of ſo ample fortunes. Earthly felicities are not unlike the Ephimera, they die the ſame day they are borne.</p>
            <p>Many yeares are required to give growth and height to a great tree, and a ſhort time ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficeth to pull it up. Let <hi>Iupiter</hi> boaſt his thun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der bolts, <hi>Iuno</hi> her ſerenes, <hi>Thetis</hi> her calmes, but Fortune in her kingdome hath things more unſtable than any of theſe. The politicke threads ſpunne by <hi>Sejanus,</hi> to weave the royall purple to himſelfe at this time, are ſooner practi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed than numbred. The tragicall ſtory of his end, (become the fable of the multitude) ſhall now be rehearſed, rather for example than de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>light. <hi>Sejanus</hi> is unworthy of compaſſion, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe unjuſt, but hee notwithſtanding is to be
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:21457:4"/> looked on with an eye of pitie, by ſuch as pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>netrate the miſery of humane condition, which hath nothing certaine, but the uncertainty of it ſelfe, and for ampleſt matter of its loſſe, the greateſt heape of its gaines.</p>
            <p>He riſeth to purchaſe either precipices or thun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders from heaven, who without ſure foundati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of merit, endevoureth to raiſe for himſelfe that mountaine of fortune which is to be aimed at by ſole vertue, and guided by the only power of that heaven, which hath reſerved to it ſelfe the authority of giving and taking away king<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>domes.</p>
            <p>Heaven threatned the ſiniſter events of <hi>Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>janus,</hi> with ſiniſter predictions, willing thereby (as it were) either to ſound a retreit to Fortune, or rather to adviſe <hi>Sejanus</hi> how little he ſhould confide in theſe our fraile felicities. Ravens ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerved, Cats enraged, the Bench whereon the Court-waiters ſate throwne downe, ſervitors by misfortune precipitated from the Caudine ſtaires, were horrid prodigies, and Portentous preſages of future calamities. Yet was there none, who on theſe things durſt make any evill con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruction, becauſe the preſent ſtate conſidered, it was no eaſie matter to beleeve an equall
<pb facs="tcp:21457:5"/> mutation might be made. <hi>Sejanus</hi> was greater than his betters, leſſe onely than his owne thoughts, and the world conceived that For<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tune could doe nothing more in him, or that there was no other Fortune but <hi>Sejanus</hi> him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe. <hi>Dion</hi> writeth, that ſuch were the founda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions of this mans greatneſſe, that had God himſelfe foretold his ruine, he would ſcarcely have beene beleeved.</p>
            <p>The Citizens ſo infinitely honoured, obſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved, reverenced, feared, adored the name of <hi>Sejanus,</hi> that <hi>Tiberius,</hi> whoſe eyes imminent perill had unvailed, began to be jealous of him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe, as well as of his Kingdome. <hi>The name of that ſubject is ever perillous to a Prince, who is more often named than himſelfe.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>To ruine ſo vaſt a frame in an inſtant, was to ſtand in danger to be oppreſſed: to ſuffer the increaſe thereof, was to oppreſſe ones ſelfe. Behold to what condition this unfortunate Prince is brought, who forgetting what hee himſelfe is, wholly reſignes himſelfe to the truſt of one man, who being raiſed to greatneſſe, (the precipice of the greateſt) hath no other fidelity, but that wherewith he is truſted.</p>
            <p>Among the people he ſaw himſelfe deſpiſed,
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:21457:5"/> but which is more, hee knew himſelfe deſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cable, as he who too baſely had ſuffered all his functions to be poſſeſſed by <hi>Sejanus,</hi> equally favoured and ſuſpected. Hee began to feare the loſſe of that authority, which (as the ſoule) guideth, and governeth all, and which as a huge pile eminenet above the reſt, falleth not, but to ruine the Kingdome.</p>
            <p>Combated by a thouſand thoughts, nay maſtered by unſpeakable feare, it behoved him rather to endevour the meannes how to recover his Empire, then preſerve it. Hee was not ignorant, that <hi>Sejanus</hi> aſcribed the Empire to himſelfe, the government of <hi>Capreae</hi> to <hi>Tiberius.</hi> Behold how Fortune had hood<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>winked this miſerable man, teaching him to dally with death. <hi>Tiberius</hi> knew it was nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther time to ſleepe, nor runne. Great remedies were needfull in ſo pregnant ſuſpitions; diſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mulation was neceſſary with a man ſo power<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full, but firſt he muſt ſeeke for ſafety, then re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venge: <hi>Moſt times the true remedy of treachery, is, to ſeeme not to know it.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>To underſtand the minde of the one and other, <hi>Caeſar</hi> began with ſtrange art to plie both <hi>Sejanus</hi> and the Senate with Letters, in
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:21457:6"/> one day varying a thouſand things concer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>himſelfe; ſometimes by declaring to them he had nothing now alive in him but infirmi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie, he confeſſed an impotencie, which ſecured <hi>Sejanus</hi> to lay more lively colours upon his deſignes; and then with his owne hand cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tifying the Senate of his health recovered, made them ſacrifice deſpite to modeſtie. By which meanes the one had a large field to ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gotiate, the other to feare. One while he prai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed <hi>Sejanus</hi> in his letters, and yet ſometime writing backe hee blamed him, magnified other of his favourites, and depreſſed others: To conclude, the whole Court depended on the uncertainty of his practiſes, which had nothing regall in them, but doubleneſſe.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Sejanus</hi> was ſometime ſuddenly puffed up with freſh favours, and as ſuddenly ſtupified with theſe unaccuſtomed proceedings. Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience aſſailed him with ſuſpition; The me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mory of predictions ſurcharged his ſoule with impreſſions of horror. It fell not into his thought to feare, beholding himſelfe ſo pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>erfull, yet dared hee as little to confide in his power, hearing ſuch novelties.</p>
            <p>Conſcience (the ſcourge of the wicked)
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:21457:6"/> permitted not he ſhould know that houre to become, wherein he muſt either conquer or die. He with all his might vapoured forth the ſmoke of his greatneſſe. He knew his practiſes were not unknowne to <hi>Tiberius,</hi> he was there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore to attempt the iſſue with violence, not expected, though doubted: For <hi>great actions ſhould rather be ſpeedily executed, than conſulted on.</hi> Death was the head of the way, flie it hee could not, well might he ennoble it. It was therefore better to meet it than expect it, ſell it than ſuffer it. Who knew, whether Fortune would not (as heretofore) favour ſudden Counſels.</p>
            <p>He muſt ſeale the concluſion with an act, if not eminent for vertue, yet memorable for hardineſſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>Dangers many times by encountring them, are avoided. Good Councels from delay, wicked from violence take force.</hi> But who un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtands not, that heaven corrupteth the councels of him, to whom the revolution of Fortune is deſtined.</p>
            <p>In the meane time the multitude (amongſt which nothing is more eaſie than change of affections) perceiving in ſo ſhort a time, ſo great alteration of affaires, began to waver.</p>
            <pb n="8" facs="tcp:21457:7"/>
            <p>They failed not to ſpread rumours of in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>novation into the eares of the people, to whom the power of <hi>Sejanus</hi> was either hate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full or ſuſpected. <hi>Each motion ſerveth for reaſon to juſt feare; with long expectation every occaſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on finds favour.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Offences heretofore tollerated, or diſſem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bled, began to be unmasked. Woe to him who hath fulfilled his felicity. There wanted not thoſe who attributed to <hi>Sejanus</hi> the blame of all <hi>Tiberius</hi> his exorbitances, compaſſionately deploring the memory of <hi>Caius Sillius,</hi> of <hi>Titus Sabinus,</hi> and <hi>Cremutius Cordus,</hi> ſo unjuſtly deprived of life.</p>
            <p>He that governeth another, walketh on a rope, which though made of golden threads, is not the more ſtable, not underſtanding how well to uſe the counterpoiſe of juſtice; If he put one foot out of the right place, the ordinary ſucceſſe is to remaine hanged.</p>
            <p>Many, not to contradict, rather than not to be ſilent, added probability to truth. Others hoping change of fortune, with alteration of government, ſeconded the beginning of his ruine, whom themſelves acknowledged for their raiſer.</p>
            <pb n="9" facs="tcp:21457:7"/>
            <p>It is very likely hee could not have beene advanced, without an infinite number of men obliged by his benefits, and yet amongſt ſo many publike invectives, there was not any one that defended him. But what! <hi>Small bene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fits are eaſily forgotten; great, ordinarily ſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>charge.</hi> Some cannot requite a good turne, other know not how. Of the ungratefull, ſome neglect it, other abhorre it. The world is come to that paſſe, that good turnes are thought dangerous. The ungratefull man, loth to repay a benefit, would not there like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe ſhould be any, to whom he may account himſelfe a debtor. Thus hapend it to poore <hi>Sejanus.</hi> The end of the obligation, and of the obliger was eſteemed an advantagious ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>change. <hi>Good, as evill equally concurreth to the oppreſsion of that unhappy man, who once be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gins to be diſtaſted.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>All the motions of <hi>Sejanus</hi> breathed forth ſadneſſe. Hee who heretofore haughty and proud, accuſtomed arrogantly to vaunt ſuper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eminencie, now wholly mortified, ſhewed how much hee was burdened with weighty cares. His eyes reconcentred with his imagi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nations, manifeſted in their wanneſſe what
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:21457:8"/> anxieties tormented him. At which time op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſed with griefe, or through diſtracted thoughts, not rendring ſalutes, he ſeemed to deſpiſe thoſe who ſaluted him, ſo that his pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per hurts unhappily conſpiring with fortune, he encreaſed the number of the malevolent, and leſſened the troops of partiall followers.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Tiberius</hi> thus judiciouſly ſpinning the web, honoured both <hi>Sejanus</hi> and his ſonne with the dignity of Prieſthood, as it were adviſing him to ſtand prepared to ſacrifice a victim to Fortune. To theſe honours he added the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conſular dignity, rather to augment doubt in the people, than titles for <hi>Sejanus;</hi> yet much would he have promiſed himſelfe by his dex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terous wit and Genius, if he could have found means to preſent himſelfe before <hi>Caeſar,</hi> where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>upon under pretext to viſit a beloved feminine ſinger of his, afflicted with a certaine infirmi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie, having ſought to come to <hi>Capreae,</hi> hee was ſuſpended by <hi>Tiberius,</hi> who would not admit his preſence, more for feare of his force, than that he refuſed the ſhorteſt and ſafeſt way to give an end to ſuch dangers, affording acceſſe for once, to bereave him of it for ever. So, <hi>ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny times it is better to tolerate by diſſembling, than
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:21457:8"/> precipitate thoſe councels, which by delay are not waſted, but fortified. In infirmity, there is not any thing more mortall, than unſeaſonable medicines.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>His eyes were darkned with horror, and mind with terror, ſeeing upon one ſide the occaſions of bounty taken away, on the other ſide, thoſe to whom he had beene bounteous, now to pay him with ingratitude. The errours committed in proſperous fortune, threatned him with adverſe. Thoſe that adhered to him, told him many things variouſly related from the people, but almoſt ever againſt him: Whereupon aſtoniſhed he loſt courage: But hope, which never failes whilſt life laſteth, comforted him; theſe feares were rather ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jects of conſcience, than incentives of pru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence. <hi>Tiberius</hi> by him unburdened from the greater toyles of Empire, ſecured from his greateſt enemies, entertained and nouſled in his chiefeſt delights: <hi>Tiberius,</hi> who found no quiet, but in the boſome of his vigilance, would not ſo ſoone (ſaid ſhee) precipitate him, whom hee ſo much had heretofore pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſed to affect. The number of allyes, obli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged friends, affectionare ſouldiers, people, who (as yet) adored him, miniſtred rather
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:21457:9"/> matter to leſſen ſorrow, than feare.</p>
            <p>This verily was the beginning of the knowledge &amp; apprehenſion that <hi>Sejanus</hi> had of the inſtability of thoſe things, which are ſubject to Fortune. Here beganne he diſcour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing with himſelfe, to derive conſequences from ſeeing, that <hi>Tiberius</hi> hitherto an impene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trable hider of his thoughts, honoured <hi>Caius</hi> with Prieſtly dignity, and praiſed him as one who ſhould ſucceed him. Here deſperation began wholly to tyrannize over thoſe rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons, which in the minde of <hi>Sejanus</hi> were fed by that moſt tormenting deſire of rule. <hi>The certainty of the ſucceſsion of a Prince, is the op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſsion of his hopes, who pretendeth to prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipalitie.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Here, as <hi>Sejanus</hi> openly loſt courage, ſo for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tune partiall to animoſity, began manifeſtly to preſecute him. A powerfull enemie of his (Prefect of <hi>Spaine)</hi> was freed from the heavie blame of exorbitant offences, whether they were reall, or objected by <hi>Sejanus. The exal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation of enemies, is the beginning of proper depreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſsion.</hi> One ſcale of the ballance goes not up, but the other ſinks downe. <hi>Tiberius</hi> wrote of the death of <hi>Nero</hi> to the Senate, and naming
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:21457:9"/> 
               <hi>Sejanus,</hi> did it without uſuall attributes. Hee forbade that any man ſhould hereafter dare to ſacrifice to a man. <hi>Poore is the God-head, whoſe Deity reſts upon an edict.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>By theſe wayes <hi>Tiberius</hi> leſſened the repu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation of the Favorite with the people, which uſeth to be the firſt and moſt grounded foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dation of greatneſſe. The troope of atten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dants to wait on him from his houſe, was not ſo frequent, becauſe ſome, not to be ſuſpected by <hi>Tiberius,</hi> (whoſe ſlie practiſes were now diſcovered) certified <hi>Sejanus</hi> of their leaving him, rather jealous of their owne good, than of anothers. The ſmokes, as well of ſacrifices on Altars, as of Pride and Ambition in the head of <hi>Sejanus,</hi> beganne to decline.</p>
            <p>His favorites were no longer honoured, and were they, it was rather in reſpect of dig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity than perſon. Injuſtice diſpoyled of the mantle of his authority, walked no longer thorow <hi>Rome,</hi> for Fortune having put guives upon it, it could not freely ſtirre up &amp; downe without danger. To theſe turmoyles, ſo much weighty as they were new, croſſe <hi>omens</hi> of predictions were added. A ſtatue of <hi>Sejanus</hi> ſmoking, the head taken off, to diſcover the
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:21457:10"/> cauſe of it, a great ſerpent was ſeene ſuddenly to iſſue forth, and the head ſet on againe, there was a knot found about the necke of it. A while after hee ſacrificing to a ſtatue of For<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tune, ſhe either not to ſee him, or becauſe ſhe could not endure him, turned her head away, ſhewing this wretched Courtier how little he ſhould confide in the vanity of that Fortune, which knowes not how to be ſtable, even in marble.</p>
            <p>Among ſuch hatefull prodigies, a thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſand torments vexed the ſoule of unhappy <hi>Sejanus.</hi> Vaine, and fruſtrate was now the thought of commotion, hee underſtanding the averſion of the people from his affaires, and knowing the Senates love towards <hi>Caius. Great attempts are atchieved in the increaſe, not diminution of fortune.</hi> We muſt not hope for ſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bility from this inconſtant Lady, whoſe favors are allwaies ſo much the more pernitious, by how much the more they render us ſecure and confident. He watched whole nights with his paines, which could ſhew him nought elſe but <hi>Chymaeras:</hi> He knew no other repoſe, but that alone, which the want of it in the boſome of toyleſome wearineſſe begat. The
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:21457:10"/> morning aire that awakened him were his ſighs, which invited him to toyle. He thought every day the laſt, every laſt would have beene deare to him, ſo it were not delayed; <hi>For much more painfull is the feare of death, than to die.</hi> (Poore <hi>Sejanus)</hi> the heape of ſo many crimes never came to deſerve, that the puniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment ſhould ſo long be deferred.</p>
            <p>A generous affection (underſtanding it was n<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ceſſary either to vanquiſh evils, or end them) awakned in his ſoule a purpoſe to with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>draw himſelfe from danger by death; to tell the world, Fortune had beene able to exalt, not depreſſe him. But the blinde warrioreſſe, who would not bereave herſelfe of the glory to have ruined him, in ſuch his ſad agonies, courted him with newes, that <hi>Tiberius</hi> ſpake of conferring the Tribunitiall power upon him, whereupon afflicting and comforting him at one and the ſame inſtant, ſhe armed him with hope, peradventure, becauſe it ſhould not bee thought a ſmall glory to her to have caſt downe a vanquiſhed man, and overcome one who begged mercy. <hi>Tiberius</hi> nothing ignorant of publike affection, and private ſuſpition, began (not deſpairing) to
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:21457:11"/> have the people and Senate on his part, to mannage the concluſion of this affaire, which carried in it ſelfe as much neceſſity, as perill. His deſigne was to levell the moſt grounded Fortreſſe of the Empire, and to pluck up the beſt rooted Plant the Earth hath nouriſhed. The pretorian Cohorts honoured, preferred, united, countenanced, fortified, by him, de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pended all on his leaſt commands. The grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſt men, who governed in the Empire, as Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fects, Queſtors, Tribunes, Captaines, and infi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nite other officers, all raiſed by him owed their ſervice, &amp; eſtate to him. The moſt inward and neareſt ſervants of <hi>Tiberius</hi> had been by his meanes deputed to that ſervice, and intimacy. The principall of the Nobility, enriched with the beſt places, either as his ſervants or Allyes, were tied to him. Of the multitude ſome were maintained in his houſe, ſome were depen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dant, ſome intereſſed; ſo that many reſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctively, and almoſt all by adherence waited on him. Well might his ruine be commanded by <hi>Tiberius,</hi> but not expected. Princes are the heart, Subjects the hands. To confide was dangerous, yet neceſſary. Strangers were no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing fit for ſo great an affaire, which required
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:21457:11"/> much knowledge of the fact, and perſons. Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miliars were to bee ſuſpected, as well for the reaſons mentioned before, as for that the moſt and beſt truſted ſervants, are thoſe, who ſoo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſt ſell their maſter. Few were not ſufficient for ſo great a buſineſſe, in many, ſecrecy was unſafe. To do it in Rome where <hi>Sejanus</hi> had the pulſe of his power, was to ſubject himſelfe to ſudden commotion of people, which is in prudence, ſo much to be avoided. To doe it out of Rome was impoſſible, or moſt diffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cult. If hee ſhould call him to Capreae hee would not come, but upon ſure conditions, bringing along with him more perill for o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, than for himſelfe. Every thing was dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gerous, and laying private intereſt aſide, no other affection would have adviſed it. In the end <hi>Tiberius</hi> excited, put forward, and enraged, peradventure more by <hi>Sejanus</hi> his unhappi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, than out of his owne wiſdome, called <hi>Nervius Sertorius Macro,</hi> and ſecretly conſtitu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting him Captaine of his Guard, hee gave him the mannage of the whole matter, adviſing him what hee was to doubt, what to avoid, what to accelerate, or ponder. He commanded him to conferre with <hi>Memmius Regulus,</hi> whoſe
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:21457:12"/> fidelity was free from ſuſpition, he being an ancient rivall of <hi>Sejanus,</hi> and ſhewed him the neceſſity of ſecrecy with the other Conſull, as being one of his enemies faction. Then, that he ſhould enſnare, and aſſault mindes with a thouſand ſorts of hopes, and feares, awaking the anger of the offended, the hatred of the reconciled, that hee ſhould fight with gold, promiſe dignities, remove ſouldiers, ſecure the armie from tumults, and finally the mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter not ſucceeding well, at the firſt ſtirres which ſhould oppoſe their deſignes, he ſhould introduce <hi>Druſus</hi> into the Senate for Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perour, by him ſo declared and pronoun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Macro</hi> departing with theſe inſtructions, <hi>Tiberius,</hi> to whom amongſt ſo many vices pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſillanimity was not wanting; not truſting to the number of his people, to the ſituation, and ſtraightneſſe of that Iland, eaſie to bee defen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded for a firſt aſſault by the ſouldiers of his guard, nothing maintaining the majeſty of his place, but having prepared many ſhips, time<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rouſly ſtood expecting opportunity of eſcape from the firſt notice, that <hi>Sejanus</hi> foreknowing his deſignes might not prevent and oppreſſe
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:21457:12"/> him. <hi>A bad Conſcience is the Mother of Feare, Feare the Father of thoſe ignoble acts, whoſe in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dignity is the Tombe of R<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>putation.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Theſe were the afflictions of <hi>Tiberius,</hi> the perills of <hi>Sejanus,</hi> the endevors of <hi>Macro,</hi> who with <hi>Tiberius</hi> his letters entring full of cares by night into Rome, began the deſigned pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctiſe with <hi>Memmius Regulus,</hi> and <hi>Gracilius Laco.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The next day the morning being come, to ſhew the laſt Sunne to <hi>Sejanus,</hi> whilſt the Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nate ſate in the Temple of <hi>Apollo, Macro</hi> en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ring in<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>o the Pallace met <hi>Seianus,</hi> whoſe ſoule, (which felt the ſtroke of Fate at hand) ſad, that <hi>Tiberius</hi> had not written to him, preſaged evill events. He was comforted by <hi>Macro's</hi> whiſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring in his eare, that he had brought him the Tribunitiall dignity; wherat joyfull, he entred into the Senate houſe, by his friends (amongſt whom this word quickly ran) honoured, reve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>renced, ſaluted, as much as by the malevolent he was feared and flattered.</p>
            <p>Behold how poore mortalls are taken in a ſnare by Fortune, unhappy he, who truſteth her; but more unhappy, who to her commits thoſe treaſures that are enriched with nought
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:21457:13"/> elſe, but others wants. <hi>Sejanus,</hi> could neither enter, nor bee received into the Senate with greater applauſe. Suſpitions, doubts paſſed, were ridiculous entertainements of preſent alacrity, as if it were humane Condition, that a little ſweet ſhould be repayed with much acerbity.</p>
            <p>Thoſe enemies who moſt hated him, doubtfull leaſt they might be diſcovered, trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted amongſt themſelves, with a ſoft murmur, (but which they notwithſtanding deſired might be heard) to conferre ſome new honor upon him, cloking their malignity, with ſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming courteous; ſecretly negotiating it, as if they did it not for oſtentation; but love. <hi>So many times diſsimulation uſeth to walke ſhame<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faſt, and reſerved, not to hide her ſelfe, but that the novelty of habit may bee of force to turne the eyes of ſuch as are preſent, upon her.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Macro</hi> having publiſhed the authority re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived from <hi>Tiberius,</hi> removed from about the Senate and <hi>Sejanus,</hi> thoſe praetorian ſoldi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers which were for a guard, and ſhewing cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine letters, in which <hi>Tiberius</hi> expreſſed hee would reward them, leaving here a good number of ſouldiers of Ceſar's guard faithfull
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:21457:13"/> by ancient ſervice, &amp; encouraged with greater hopes, he led the Praetorians to their ſtations, that no innovation might bee made. In the mean time <hi>Tiberius</hi> his letter was read, brought by him to the Senate, which verily was long, as being ſtuffed with a thouſand cunning po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>licies. In the beginning it contained diverſity of affaires, afterward with a ſhort complaint of <hi>Sejanus</hi> as with a ſlight inquiſition, he prepared minds to greater matters. Then paſſing to o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther affaires, he in a while returned to complain of hi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> and commanding that two Senators, the moſt intimate with <hi>Sejanus,</hi> ſhould be pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhed, ordained in the manner of an entreaty, grounded &amp; neceſſitated upon ſuſpitions, and State-rules, that <hi>Sejanus</hi> himſelfe ſhould be un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dercuſtody. Requiring that one of the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuls ſhould be aſſigned to wait on himſelf, that he might come to <hi>Rome</hi> in ſafety.</p>
            <p>Let him meaſure and argue upon the en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>devour of this letter, who from the things ſaid before, underſtandeth the ſuſpition of <hi>Tiberius.</hi> Let that poore Courtier penetrate the ſudden effect of it, who knoweth how head<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>long Fortune is to throw one downe from greatneſſe. <hi>The deſcent from height, hath no leſſer
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:21457:14"/> ſteps then a leap. Moſt times no diſtinction may be made betweene the ſupremeſt, and loweſt fortune.</hi> It is impoſſible that the penne ſhould ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtaine from flattering the eyes, whilſt it be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wailes humane infelicity on theſe papers. No ſooner was the Letter read, but thoſe Senators haſtily roſe up, who moſt faithfull, moſt deare ſate about <hi>Sejanus,</hi> deteſting him, whom hitherto they had ſoothed, ſerved, and adored. When Fortune departs, ſhee carries friends away with her. They, who once were of his faction, ſtrove to be the firſt to forſake him, boaſting to be the formoſt in ſeconding the will of Caeſar. Out alas, that friends fly the place, where they are tryed. <hi>Profit and delight are thoſe intereſts, which gaine love: Friendſhip is that ſonne, who is allwaies buried with his Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther.</hi> By that which his deareſt friends did, may be argued what his enemies endevoured. They emulouſly roſe up to accuſe, calumniate, reproach him, and all the exorbitant exceſſes, not onely of <hi>Tiberius,</hi> but of the moſt abject creatures (unknowne to <hi>Sejanus)</hi> were aſcri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bed to him. There was not any, who was ſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent in his cauſe, and if there were, it was either to give time, that the multitude of accuſations
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:21457:14"/> might not be loſt, or to recommend them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves to the goddeſſe <hi>Memory,</hi> to ſuggeſt new cauſes of complaints. The Pretors, and Tribunes encompaſſed him round about, doubtful, leaſt he might get out to ſtir the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple to commotion: A wary diligence, but need<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>les, becauſe feare (the ſergeant that waitson co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience) had before any other tied up his ſenſes in ſuch knots of dejection, that I ſuppoſe leſſer were not neceſſary to hold a proud ſoule from abandoning manhood in ſo ſudden a change.</p>
            <p>Who will vaunt himſelf of thoſe greatneſſes which as they may be acquired, may conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quently be loſt. <hi>Regulus,</hi> and <hi>Laco</hi> dragged him as guilty out of the Senate, at whoſe feet juſtice, and fortune had ſo long lyen proſtrate. The people, lovers of novelties, ran together crying out a loud, &amp; curſing <hi>Sejanus,</hi> to whoſe houſe (calling him the companion of <hi>Caeſar)</hi> they but halfe an hower before haſtened to wait on him.</p>
            <p>The ſouldiers, who heretofore uſed to glory in his ſervice, boſted themſelves &amp; grew proud at his captivity. They who before had adored him for a <hi>god,</hi> &amp; honored him as a prieſt, haled him as a victim to ſacrifice. And ſo grievous,
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:21457:15"/> and certaine was the ignominy imminent o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver the preſent perill, that it was raſhnes to en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vie one of thoſe Oxen, which were ſacrificed to him in the former flouriſh of Fortune. Oh how little is the affection of the people to be truſted, who ſo eaſily adore and murther men, that they cannot learne to pardon their owne gods, not reverenced for the power of their thunderbolts; but made, and deified by their proper hands.</p>
            <p>The name of the unfortunate <hi>Sejanus,</hi> was not onely the ſport of fortune, but of the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple likewiſe; the ſoules by him deprived the benefit of this pretious light ranne up and down, with a thouſand whippes to excite, and enrage as well his owne Conſcience, as the multitude, againſt him. Every one agreed to mocke him for thoſe his elevated thoughts, which were to ſinke at the foot of the Gemo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nian ſtayres. His ſtatues were the Center of Speares and Swords. Let not the Load-ſtone boaſt to attract Iron with greater force, then did the marbles inſcribed with the name of <hi>Sejanus.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>This is that memorable day, wherein the impious barbariſme of the people taught him
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:21457:15"/> to die, who had never lived. Brazen modells were no longer melted with fire, but with wounds, for in the forge of Rome no other fewell burnt, but of indignation, nor any other bellowes were blowne, but of Anger.</p>
            <p>For no other cauſe had fortune rayſed ſo many ſtatues to him, but to multiply an infi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity of <hi>Sejanns'es</hi> which ſhould at this inſtant be the miſerable prey of a thouſand torments, as though <hi>Sejanus</hi> were not capable enough of ſo many puniſhments, who only ſufficed to commit ſo many crimes. There was not any one who ſought not to get ſome relique of him, to preſerve it as the miracle of Fortune.</p>
            <p>Exorbitancies of cruelty reflecting from the eye to the minde, afflicted the poore <hi>Sejanus;</hi> his ſoule oppreſſed with ſo inſupportable acci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dents, languiſhed, for the griefe of dying, yet would death have been the laſt of all evils, had it not drawne along with it ſo much ig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nominy. For finally <hi>to go out of life is neceſſary, but to be driven from it is ſhamefull.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>What may wee beleeve, was the paſſage of this unhappy man from the Senate to the pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon? He endevoured to cover his head, to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſend himſelfe, I know not whether from
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:21457:16"/> ſhame or injury, but as he could not hide him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe from his owne conſcience, ſo they diſco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verd him to the eyes of others. Fortune ſcor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned to triumph over a man masked, and hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven thought it not a puniſhment equall for demerit, to hide him from thoſe who had bin ſpectators of his crimes, and were the remain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders of his fury.</p>
            <p>They all cryed out, ſtormed, and exclaimed to have him killed; that he ſhould be precipi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tated, who was the death and ruine of the Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pire. The weakeſt cowards learnt courage, from the example of the ſtrongeſt, the ſtron<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geſt envied the horror of the weakeſt, finding themſelves unable to maintaine that fury, which ſtirred them up to revenge. The breſt of <hi>Sejanus</hi> would have been the ſepulcher of a thouſand ſwords, nor would the ſouldiers who environed him have ſufficed to preſerve him, had it not bin for fortune, who was deſirous alſo to enjoy this laſt delight, to ſee a Hang<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man envied by a hundred Senators; every ſtep was a death, every death was ſo much the more grievous, as it had the more of life. The paſſage of dying is a moment; and that which is diſpatched in a moment, is no great evill; but
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:21457:16"/> this was ſo much the greater an evill, by how much the more they delayd him that death, which might take him from the ignominy which the eies ſaw, and from the torments which ſenſe feared.</p>
            <p>Being come to the priſon, either the frozen heart denied paſſage to the ſoule, or elſe the ſoule oppreſſed with ſo many objects, of ſtu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pifying paine, found not out the way to liber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, otherwiſe, if we thinke how little experien<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced, he was of ſiniſter fortune, or if we weigh the ſorrow of loſſe, by the value, by the horror of death, and by the feare of conſcience, it had beene impoſſible hee ſhould have lived a moment.</p>
            <p>Let him not compaſſionate the miſery of this wretched Courtier, who is not expoſed to misfortune: And who knoweth not, that the moſt wretched manner of unhappineſſe, is, to have once bin happy. If he deſerve not pity as <hi>Sejanus,</hi> he deſerves it as a man become miſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable. <hi>Every occaſion ſhould ſerve the juſt man to exerciſe his vertue. Courtefie, benefits, and clemen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cie, are the three means wherewith he who gover<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth, ought to oblige the minds and affections of the people, without which, Empire is nought elſe but a
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:21457:17"/> perillous ſervitude.</hi> It is true, that diſcretion ought to be the diſtributreſſe of theſe trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſures; That overmuch curteſie begets con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempt; That benefits rather ſcattered, than placed oblige not, and indulgence not limi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted is a ſecurity in ſinning, it being ordinarily the condition of men not to know how to beare all ſlavery, nor all liberty. The neglect of theſe bounds, not knowne or not obſerved, afflicted the poore <hi>Sejanus,</hi> the infelicity of whoſe pollicy had found more greatneſſe, than ſafety. <hi>Never was that power either ſtable, or laſting, which was gained by wickedneſſe.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>An Idaea cannot be framed in the minde of any mortall man of a more exact ſtates-man, then that, which then in a Chymaera preſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted it ſelfe to the minde of <hi>Sejanus,</hi> made wiſe by the unhappineſſe of his fortune. He abhor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red his former pride; it vexed him hee had ſet himſelfe as the ſcope of Envy. The Oſtentati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of <hi>Tiberius</hi> his favor, the violence of emula<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tors, his having arrogated to himſelfe Empire over that world that now refuſed to ſupport him, were ſuch puniſhments, as they were not onely preambles, but lively touches of the Torments of hell, affording no ſpace either for
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:21457:17"/> hope or amendment. Now (although late) hee ſaw how dangerous it was to play with the Lion, who concludeth his daliances with his pawes. Affections ſo long felt, or to ſay better, ſuffered, made themſelves underſtood to be lyers. They a little before had the face of hopes, and now were knowne to be dotages. But what knew he not? Vnhappineſſe taught the miſerable man, that which prudence hath written in her books: not at this time to make h<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>m cautious, but rather ſo much the more ſad. From matters whence felicity drawes good, miſery derives evill, nor can a greater miſchiefe afflict a miſerable man, than to be reduced to that point, that even prudence it ſelfe concurreth to render him unhappy.</p>
            <p>In the meane ſpace the Senate ſeeing none of the innovations, then feared either from the ſouldiers, who with hopes had beene brought by <hi>Macro</hi> to the Legions, or from the people that followed his miſery, to whoſe Fortune they had tied themſelves by an invio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lable oath, aſſembling together in the Temple of Concord, that they might not be reduced to ſuch ſtraights, as to deſire that which now the people expected from them, they con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demned
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:21457:18"/> the miſerable <hi>Sejanus</hi> to puniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment.</p>
            <p>Ah poore condition of man, Beares, and Lyons are fed for Gladiators, and men are fatned for the ſithe of death. <hi>Tiberius,</hi> durſt not command the death of <hi>Sejanus,</hi> and his ſervants durſt execute it. The people ſtormed at retardation, finding more puniſhment in delay, then the delinquent was to feele in the execution. <hi>Every thing ſubmits to fortune, which never embraceth man, but to ſtrangle him.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>One ſole hower ſufficed to accuſe, arraigne, condemne, and execute a monarch ſo much greater than others, by how much they had commanded over an Empire, he over the Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perour.</p>
            <p>Among ſo many his allyes, friends, ſoldiers, followers, dependents, miniſters, there was not one ſtirred a foot for him, nay, there was not one who ſtirred not a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt him. Every one runnes for wood to the tree, which the winde or hatchet hath layd along. At this time there could bee no greater offence, nor perill, then fidelity; He was a true ſervant, who moſt ſpeedily haſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:21457:18"/> the death of his Maſter, to free him from thoſe miſeries, which were not to moove mercie in any other Deity, then death.</p>
            <p>Concord was aſhamed to bee at ods with Fortune, and lent her, her owne Temple to be a Theater, where the Sentence of this mans death ſhould bee pronounced, and conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quently the monitory of humane infelicity. Betweene the condemnation, and execution, nothing interpoſed, but the diſtance, which was betwixt the priſon, and thoſe ſtaires, from whence the condemned muſt diſmount in a leap, from ſupremeſt exaltation, to the loweſt miſery. He was taken from priſon with ſuch fury, that we may rather ſay hee flew thence. They dragged him to the precipice, and threw him headlong from the top. Let him imagine the manner, who hath the heart to thinke of it. No injury, or poſſible cruelty was omitted to be uſed, nay rather, that was made poſſible, which was not; for to ſee the ally, the obliged, the ſervant, the friend to lead trium<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phantly to death, his greater, his benefactor, his Lord, is a ſpectacle more true than likely. They that were neareſt were ambitious to have the
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:21457:19"/> opportunity to abuſe him, the moſt diſtant followed him, ſorry they could not have a hand in this action. Some curſed him, ſome upbraided him with his acts, and both the one and the other ſhewed him his puniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, to increaſe the ſorrow with the terror, and augment the manner, although not the numbers of his death. Oh people, alike cruell in puniſhing, and in having ſo long deferred the chaſtiſement.</p>
            <p>Behold to what this man is reduced, whoſe favour men no longer deſired, to whom ſtarres afforded no gratious influences, nor Fortune gave bleſſings. That man, with whoſe revenges hell was increaſed, and to whoſe ſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tues the <hi>gods</hi> envied the beſt ſacrifices. Oh how much more ſecure is the povertie of <hi>Irus,</hi> than the riches of <hi>Creſſus. That Engine, which more than other is raiſed toward Heaven, more than the reſt approacheth thunders. Let him avoid the aſcent, who feares the precicipice. He that will enjoy the Court, let him not pretend to greatneſſe with a Prince. He, who would know what great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe with a Prince is, let him make his laſt Will, for it is nought elſe but ſudden ruine.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Theſe are Aphoriſmes ſubſcribed by a cay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive,
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:21457:19"/> whoſe body could never finde repoſe, not ſo much as in the boſome of death. The earth denied buriall to the corps of him who had filled ſo many Sepulchers with his cru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eltie. Friends defrauded it of that ſepulture, to which for the ſakes of the living, rather than of the dead, enemies themſelves uſe to be courteous. Poore <hi>Sejanus,</hi> for an eternall re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuge, found not two yards of that land, whoſe vaſt Continent he had both commanded and governed.</p>
            <p>Scarcely arrived he to the end of the laſt leape, rent, torne, and diſmembred, but that the people for three whole dayes dragged him thorowout <hi>Rome,</hi> bathing the ſtones with his bloud, who had ſtained them with the bloud of poore Citizens. After this, they on the fourth day threw him into the River, either that he ſhould not returne to infect <hi>Rome,</hi> or that <hi>Tiber</hi> might begin to be more fertile in monſters than the Sea. Behold the continued courſe of Fate, water was ever the Supulcher of <hi>Icarus'es</hi> and <hi>Phaetons.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Fortune permitted not it ſhould come into the peoples minds, to waſte the remainders of this miſerable carkaſſe with fire, becauſe ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:21457:20"/> expoſed it to the cruelty of men, ſhee would likewiſe reſerve it to the ſhames of na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, to exerciſe its corruptions upon him. He, who had beene fed with the bloud and wealth of poore Citizens, was reſerved to feed fiſhes in the water, wormes in the earth, and birds in the ayre. Oh never enough ado<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red divine Providence!</p>
            <p>The funerals celebrated for this unhappy creature, ought rather to be abbreviated, than enlarged for writing them, there is not any one will beleeve them, and to credit them is hardly in man, for the impiety thereof ſurpaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed the inhumanity of man.</p>
            <p>The Orators were curſes and reproaches. The ſacrificers, cruelty and fury. The chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren and friends of <hi>Sejanus</hi> were the victims. The houſes of the dead were purged from crimes with fire; The fires were quenched with the bloud of his faction. The diverſity of times made it equally dangerous to have offended, and to have loved <hi>Sejanus. There is not any ſacrifice of a worſe condition, then that of envie.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Mercy appeared not in the Palace that day, for innocencie was a crime, and he was not
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:21457:20"/> without crime, who became not an enemie to <hi>Sejanus.</hi> Behold how unſound is the friend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip of an unjuſt Favorite.</p>
            <p>There burnt nothing of pity to the ſoule of that unhappy man, but ſome fire of re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venge, ſince under the title of <hi>Sejanus</hi> his friends, private enemies were purſued. <hi>In po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pular commotion, it is alwayes the ſureſt way to retire.</hi> The Praetorian ſouldiers mutined, that the night-guards were preferred before them in matter of fidelity. Many Citizens were accuſed and condemned for his friend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip, ſome of which <hi>(Marcus Terentius</hi> excepted, whom Courage, Iuſtice, and Fortune aſſiſted) unfortunately ſtood upon their defence, which nought availed them, unleſſe it were to give time, that the other Complices might be throwne headlong from the Capitoll; and becauſe one kinde of death could not ſerve ſo great a number of proſcribed, many ſlew themſelves.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Tiberius</hi> not confiſcating the goods of him who prevented the Hangman (to avoid the imputation of cruelty, which others execu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted) barbarouſly enforced men, who were deſirous to leave rich heires, to kill themſelves.</p>
            <pb n="36" facs="tcp:21457:21"/>
            <p>Behold death reduced to be the utmoſt, not of things terrible, but of mens goods; where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in ſo much was gained in an inſtant, as was poſſeſſed through the whole courſe of life. See how true it is, that <hi>among mortall things there is not any more fading, than that power, which hath not ſupport from it ſelfe.</hi> Thus was the whole day ſpent in wickedneſſes, the laſt of which was the generall joy that was made. This was a day dedicated to cruelty, in which the miſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable <hi>Sejanus</hi> ſaw, nay felt the ſetting of his greatneſſe, to bee the chaſtiſement of his crimes.</p>
            <p>Vnhappy he who confides in his own great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe. <hi>Poore is that power which reſts in the breſt of one man. Vnfortunate is that man who depen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth on another.</hi> Let the Courtier learne true politike arts, from the Hiſtory of this wretch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed forlorne creature. Happy he, who ſtudieth prudence on anothers bookes.</p>
            <p>Let the Favorite of a Prince flie violence, as a thing which cannot continue. Let him flie Envie, againſt which none can long perſiſt. Let him not raiſe his greatneſſe on terrour and cruelty, for they afford a great man more feare than power, more perill than ſafety. Let
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:21457:21"/> him rule with a ſlacke hand, who would be lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved; but yet with that temper, without which vertue concludes in vice. <hi>Terror and feare are too weake bands to tie minds; when once they are looſe, who leave to feare thee, they will begin to hate thee.</hi> Flie oſtentation, as the mother of Envie, as the daughter of Vanity. <hi>He who cannot in himſelfe containe the favour of his Lord, ſhewes himſelfe to be incapable, and conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quently undeſerving.</hi> Let him ſuffer himſelfe to be honoured, as enforced, not as preten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding it, aſcribing honours to his office, not to merit. Let him carry himſelfe towards a Prince with reverence, and this is a flattery without vice. Theſe are the Brokers of favour, becauſe the common defects of great ones is pride, as thoſe who meaſure themſelves by their for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tune, not by their merit. Let him eſteeme the fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour of a Prince, as a thing which may be loſt. Let him not run to honours, but expect them, not as one who ſeekes them, but deſerves them; not as a neceſſary ſervant, but as a good. Of every thing that ſucceeds well with him, acknowledging none from proper prudence, let him aſcribe all to the vertue, to merit, to the fortune of the Prince. Let him not labour
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:21457:22"/> for vanity, but juſtice, for merit conſiſteth not in well diſſembling, but well doing. Ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry ill can vice cloke it ſelfe with the habits of vertue, neither doth the Aſſe dance to the Harpe, nor the Lyon's skinne teach us to rore.</p>
            <p>Let him not abuſe the favour of his Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tron, which would bee either to deſpiſe it, or not to know it. Let him acknowledge it, as a gift, not as a reward: ſo doing, other will endevour to deſerve it that they may obtaine it, and hee will likewiſe deſerve it, whilſt hee obtaines it. In the affaires of a Prince let him uſe diligence, ſollicitude, and counſell; In Counſells, ſincerity, and ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crecie. <hi>No leſſe is ſecrecie neceſſary, than good counſell.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Let him not bee perpetually by his Lords ſide for profit, and riches. With many to have heaped riches, hath not been the end of evills, but the mutation. When the Prince hath given all, and the Favorite can deſire no more, they quickly grow weary one of another. Let him rather beg modeſtly, than impor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tunately. Let him reſt ſatisfied with conve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niency, and not pretend to over-much;
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:21457:22"/> for <hi>hee knowes not how to beginne to enjoy, who cannot tell where to make an end of ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving.</hi> Vomiting is the Phyſician of Reple<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion. Let the Favourite bee content with what hee may have, for when the Prince hath given all hee hath, to take it backe a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaine, it is neceſſary hee ſhould reſume that which hee before gave, and becauſe to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſume is ſhamefull, many times hee is ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken out of his ſight, who makes him a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhamed.</p>
            <p>Let <hi>Papinian,</hi> Let <hi>Seneca</hi> ſpeake, for whom it was a thing impoſſible to avoid riches, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe they ſhowred upon them; It was not lawfull to refuſe them, for they were the gifts of a Prince. What Felicity then is this, where hee who hath it, feares, who would have it, is unſafe, and who would refuſe it, cannot?</p>
            <p>Let him profeſſe himſelfe to be leſſe with his equalls, To be courteous, and affable: for they who are ſuch, have had of their e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nemies greater friends, than the other of their Citizens. Sometimes let him participate the favors of his lord with them, not as a man who gives them, but begs them. To goe about to
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:21457:23"/> give them, is a profeſſion of ſuperiority; a matter odious among equals: <hi>Proud favours reape contempt, &amp; ingratitude in ſtead of thanks. In the mannage of State-affaires,</hi> where ſecrecie is not enjoyned, let him communicate with them, as well to avoid the note of one who arrogateth all to his owne authority, as to erre, rather with the opinion of many, than by himſelfe alone. <hi>The ſucceſſe of an affaire provi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth protectors for him, who conſulteth it with others.</hi> To aske counſell, is to honour him of whom it is required, yet is not liberty taken away from a man to doe as he pleaſeth. It is true, the quality of the perſon is to bee obſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved. <hi>For to aske counſell of ones better, is to bee tied to performance.</hi> In a buſineſſe whereon thou haſt conſulted, good ſucceſſe will be thy glory, evill thy excuſe, having followed the advice of others.</p>
            <p>Profeſſe equality with inferiours, not of manners, that it become not baſeneſſe, but of pretentions. In commands be diſcreet, for <hi>be who, ſeldome or never commands, is alwayes obeyed.</hi> Let the manner of commanding bee by way of intreaty, for although his intreaty who hath authority to command containe
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:21457:23"/> violence, let him notwithſtanding doe it, for he ſhall be obeyed with promptneſſe, which he may make uſe of for good manners, not obligation. Let him be milde, that too much ſeverity keepe not inferiours ſo diſtant that he cannot afterward employ them in his need. Let him be liberall in words, <hi>for the gifts of poore Princes are favours, which coſt nothing.</hi> Let him be free of his deeds, if he be able, for <hi>a benefit is the father of a benefit, and love is a fortreſſe to defend greatneſſe.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Let him uſe a lenitive with detractors of his honour, and the malevolent to his perſon. Let his ſcope be the end of the ill will, not of the ill willer. Exerciſing power againſt him, no place will remaine to exerciſe vertue. <hi>There is no enemie whom benefits will not gaine.</hi> Thou maiſt have great hopes of his friendſhip, whoſe enmity hath found thee doing favours. <hi>To kill a competitor in State-affaires, is too full of danger.</hi> Suddenly the Prince beginneth to ſuſpect an exceſſe of imaginations in thy mind. Little can the head confide in him, who hath not borne reſpect to its members. The people begin to feare, and hate thy greatneſſe; and for that vertue borders neare upon vice, thy
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:21457:24"/> ſolicitous care is judged intereſt, reverence, adulation, and juſtice, ſeverity: Beſides, <hi>power grounded upon miſchiefe, was never long.</hi> Let him flie affaires odious to the people, for there is no force againſt hatred, which can availe: If he cannot decline them, let him ſhew him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe to bee the ſervant, not the ſuperiour, a diſſwader, not a counſellour. Let him be the firſt to ſtand expoſed to hurt. Let him execute his office with charity, not predominancie. Let him give time, expect time, comfort, en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courage, aſſiſt; <hi>for promptneſſe overcommeth every difficulty, and the glory will not be unwor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy the danger.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Let him remember, that the life of great men is nought elſe but a perpetuall cenſure, and <hi>where cenſure is in continuall uſe, greatneſſe is not laſting.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Finally, let him be that within himſelfe, which he would be accounted by other. Let him endevour to be vertuous, for <hi>vertue is it's owne reward.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Every man can envie the proſperity of for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tune; in vertue even fortune her ſelfe finds what to envie. This alone addes a ſtraine of immortality to him, who is mortall. <hi>He is not
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:21457:24"/> happy on whom treaſures ſhowre; but that man whoſe good reſts in the mind.</hi> Well may fortune pricke him, not wound him; ſtrike him, not overthrow him. Adverſity, loſſes, injuries; can doe that againſt vertue, which clouds may againſt the Sunne. It is true, that the Courtier (being perfectly ſuch) will come to bee (as it were) no Courtier; for the Court is the receptacle of all fraud and vice; Let him therefore ſeeke to accoaſt the beſt what hee may; for the vertuous man knowes how to tread the paths of vice with an upright foot, and verily honeſt men can, and un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtand how to live, even under bad Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces. There is no other meanes to overcome Fortune, but by ſole vertue; and although the juſt man is not free from the effects, yet is he exempt from the occaſions; For if hee bee afflicted, hee is afflicted as a man, not as wicked, nay rather hee is exerciſed, as vertuous. <hi>Attalus</hi> the Stoicke ſaid, I rather chooſe Fortune ſhould entertaine mee in her toiles than in her delights. I am tor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mented, but I beare it couragiouſly; I am killed, but I die valiantly. This goeth well; unhappineſſe is the fire which purifieth
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:21457:25"/> this gold. <hi>Fortune truſteth no man more than him who deſpiſeth her, none deſpiſe her but the vertuous, and although every fortune faile us, it is no meane fortune to be vertuous.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But what ſaid I of Fortune? Man hath no other fortune but himſelfe. Who is ſo ſimple as not to know it, who ſo wicked as to deny it.</p>
            <p>That <hi>Sejanus</hi> was in one inſtant adored and precipitated; raiſed to eminent height, de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſed to loweſt abjectneſſe; environed by ſo many friends, beſieged by ſo many ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies; not defended by any, perſecuted by all, I confeſſe to be no ſmall matter, yea ſuch, that not injuriouſly men ſought to cover it with ſupernaturall power, conſtituting an imaginary Deity, to predominate over theſe exorbitances of motion.</p>
            <p>But what ſhould a Prince doe, (ſpeaking naturally) ſeeing himſelfe oppreſſed, betrayed, entrapped by a force, which takes all force from his favour; which in ſtead of gratefully ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledging him, ſeekes perfidiouſly to ru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ine him? If the chaſtiſement of ſo great a diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>order be committed to fortune, what aſſured<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of ſtrength defends him? If a great one depoſe not a leſſer, who offends him, what is
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:21457:25"/> this greatneſſe? And if this bee not naturall, to what purpoſe did nature put into us, that motion of anger towards revenge?</p>
            <p>That friends in theſe calamities abandon the depoſed, is not accidentall, but neceſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry. <hi>The preſervation of the Individuum, is the moſt principall among all the effects of nature.</hi> Who ſeeth not, that a private man following the adherence to a Rebell againſt a Prince, of neceſſity is a companion of his crimes and fortune? Hee wrongs no man, who vertu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſly maketh uſe of his Reaſon; It is the natu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall reaſon of every one who is borne, what he can to ayd, preſerve, and defend his owne life; and even thus much is granted, which ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times hath happened, that to preſerve it with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out any fault, men have been killed; and this thelawes admit (under the care of which is the preſervation of each mortall) how much more lawfull then is it, without offence to any for a good Courtier to abandon a friend, not friendſhip; and to retire from perill, not from love?</p>
            <p>That in one and the ſame time a thouſand are diſcovered to be enemies, who have flat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tered thee, is no wonder; man being promptly
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:21457:26"/> diſpoſed to arrive by what meansſoever to his own ends. The place, thou emptieſt hath need to be repleniſhed. That the ſubject flatters his Prince, is not againſt nature. That revenge ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pects occaſion, is not unuſuall. They, who now are thy enemies, were never thy friends; Vertue admits no change. That enemies of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fend thee, is no mervell, it were ſtrange if they help thee. That <hi>Sejanus</hi> was precipitated from ſo exalted a Condition of felicity into ſo deep a dungeon of miſery, is not to bee called an effect of fortune; for if the cauſes (as we ſaw before) be of nature, how can the effects bee ſupernaturall? Man is that ſilke worme, which hath woven a priſon, and bands for it ſelf, and when crimes cometo incorrigible terms, they incur by divine permiſſion thoſe chaſticeme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ts, which naturally follow bad beginnings. Who ſees not, that ruine waiteth on him, who plaies over it. Every Autumn concludeth in Winter. Mirth endeth in teares. The Souldier is reſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved to the Sword, the Marriner to the waves. It is not aſcribed to Fortune, that a Butterfly, bold to dally with the fire, at laſt is waſted in the flame, and is it to be called an accident of fortune, that that man, who is not able to
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:21457:26"/> governe himſelfe, fals oppreſſed under the weight of the government of a whole world, and that which is more conſiderable, of ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther mans world? As if it were leſſe naturall to returne backe, then to depart from, to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcend than to climbe.</p>
            <p>Fortunate is that Courtier, who to gaine the favour of his Lord, makes vertue the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrument. Happy he, who having obtained it, retires, that he may not loſe it. The end at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained, he who further pretendeth, provoketh miſery. He commits himſelfe to aiery vanity, to gaine the certainty of a Center, who deſcen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth from a height, not expecting to bee throwne headlong. The meaſure of the foot is more ſafe than of the eye. Favour is not in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>acceſſible, but to preſerve it is impoſſible, or difficult. The prize is gotten at the end, not at the beginning of the race. The end of good events, is the beginning of bad. <hi>He who truſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth to himſelfe is raſh, who confideth in the favour of another, is meerely mad. The laſt day of ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vitude, is the firſt of libertie.</hi> Liberty in a gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous and vertuous minde, is a pledge which aſſureth thee that ſuch ſhall be thy fortune, as thou canſt make it or deſire it.</p>
            <pb n="48" facs="tcp:21457:27"/>
            <p>This is as much as I can ſay to thee (O Courtier.) The favour of great men is an allu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring <hi>Syren,</hi> which hath poyſon on the tongue, and a ſword in hand. Let <hi>Sejanus</hi> be thy ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter, not thy guide, for very fond is he, who walketh on ruines, and remembers not hee may fall.</p>
            <epigraph>
               <q>
                  <bibl>IUVENAL.</bibl>
                  <l>—Qui nimios optabat honores</l>
                  <l>Etnimias poſcebat opes, numero ſa parabat</l>
                  <l>Excelſae turris tabulata, unde altior eſſet</l>
                  <l>Caſus, &amp; impulſae praeceps immane ruinae.</l>
               </q>
            </epigraph>
            <trailer>FINIS:</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:21457:27"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
